what happened to uncle uncle Just
что с дядей случилось дядя Как раз таки
went to s he was
поехал на с его
called up and a Ukrainian drone flew into their
призвали и украинский Дрон влетел в их
car and exploded and he died they kept him
машину и взорвался и он умер его хранили
in a closed
в закрытом
coffin
гробу
hello let's have a normal
здравствуйте давайте нормально
conversation
пообщаемся
let's have a normal conversation
давайте нормально пообщаемся
I have a
У меня
cheni let it be a [ __ ] everything is fine
чени пусть будет [__] всё нормально
not this already ST doby  I understand you yes by 19
не это уже СТ доби понял Вам да по по 19
18 years old everything everything is simple suddenly children then I
18 лет всё всё просто вдруг дети то я с
don’t talk to children so I’m from Ukraine
детьми не разговариваю так я из Украины
but I don’t quarrel I want to
но я не ссорюсь я вот хочу у Россиян
ask Russians their opinion how they see us
спросить ихнее мнение как они видят нас
people from Ukraine do you have
людей из Украины есть ли у вас на нас
any-  then maybe I have a resentment, my ex-
какие-то обиды может у меня бывший
boyfriend is from Ukraine, like I'm
молодой человек из Украины типа я сама
Ukrainian myself, yes, and
украинка да А живёте
you live in Russia, Russia, well, territorially, that
Мы в России России ну территориально это
's Moscow, St.
там Москва
Petersburg, we're in Smolensk, Slen, Smolensk, I
Питер мы в Смоленске Слен Смоленск
understand. I wonder what your attitude is toward
понял Интересно а как относитесь к
Ukrainians, toward
украинцам к
war, well, toward war, negatively, because
войне Ну к войне негативно потому что
that's the same thing.  it affects us to some
это же и на нас влияет в какой-то
extent, but it is basically neutral towards Ukrainians
степени а к украинцам в принципе
because why
нейтрально потому что ну зачем
treat people badly considering that
относиться к народу плохо с ум того что
I
я сама
myself My mother was Ukrainian  and everything before it and
У меня мама была украинка и все до неё и
after it That is, as if I don’t see
после неё То есть как бы я не вижу этом
anything bad in this I’m against war, more precisely, my own,
ничего плохого я против войны точнее сво
that
то
is, and what do you think How should
есть а как вы считаете Как должна
this
закончиться эта
war end Well, we all know how it will end
война Ну все мы знаем как она закончится
How I don’t know yet how it will end Well, for
как я не знаю пока как закончится Ну для
whom  - it will end badly maybe
кого-то она плохо закончится может быть
for Russia it will end badly Well that
для России она закончится плохо Ну то
is, one side will
есть какая-то сторона всё равно А
suffer from this war in any case
пострадает от этой войны в любом случае
that is It doesn't matter who for what reason Well in
то есть Неважно кто почему то есть Ну в
any case
любом случае какая-то вот осадок
some kind of sediment will remain anyway fathers like  fathers
останется один фиг отцы типа отцы
sons will not return What difference does it make what the
сыновья не вернутся Какая разница какой
outcome will be that is already Yes if Like
будет исход то есть уже Да если Типа
people like will die I have already been to the pans you have
люди типа умрут Я уже была на панах вас
among your acquaintances who have already
у вас среди знакомых есть которые уже
died yes yes many yes enough These are
погибли да да много да достаточно Это
some relatives distant acquaintances
какие-то родственники дальние знакомые
who is this This is like well the most  here is a recent
кто это Это типа ну самый вот недавний
case I kept I had a guy at the moment
случай Я хранила у менят момент был
I kept
парень я на свой день рождения хранила
his own uncle on my birthday like I stood keeping
его родного дядю типа я стояла хранила
him And what happened to the uncle And what happened to the uncle
его А что с дядей слу А что с дядей
And the uncle Just went to
случилось А дядя Как раз-таки поехал на
his
с его
call and the Ukrainian Drone flew into  their
призвали и украинский Дрон влетел в их
car and exploded and he died they
машину и взорвался и он умер его
buried him in a closed
хоронили в закрытом
coffin here in Smolensk we also have a Drone
гробу вот у нас в Смоленске тоже Дрон
We have a lot of drones E like
Дронов очень много у нас Э типа вот у
at that moment my boyfriend
меня на тот момент Мой молодой человек
He is a military man and he is under threat of
Он военный и он находится под угрозой
an explosion so Smolensk is far from
взрыва так Смоленск - Это же далеко от
Ukraine is through Belarus this is the border
Украины это же через Белорус это граница
this is the Border on the border We are on the border Well
это Граница на границе Мы на границе Ну
you are not on the border you are on the border with
вы не на границе вы на границе с
Belarus not with Ukraine So what
Белоруссию не с Украиной Так а какая
difference does it make we are very close we are the closest
разница то очень близко мы ближе всех
we are under the red zone
находимся мы под красной зоной на нас
like drones are flying at us not Here is mine  the young
летят типа дроны не Вот мой молодой
man tells me to stay at home
человек передаёт чтобы я сидела дома
because they flew into our city like a
потому что в наш город ти влетают вот
year and a half ago or like 2
сколько полтора года назад или типа 2
years ago they blew up some kind of plant And I
года назад взорвали завод какой-то А я
saw Smolensk
видел смоленс
So what about
Да так чтом
Belgorod for them there so
Белгород им вообще там так
we are 2 hours away from Bryansk yeah yeah  it's
мы нам до Брянска 2 часа да а да это
really close Yes, we are very close
вообще близко Да мы очень близко
Yes, and what do people say, they are tired and afraid of
Да а что люди говорят устали уже боятся
all this Well, yes, they are tired But we are already
этого всего Ну да устали Но мы уже
used to it, here I am like from Siberia, they
привыкли вот у нас я сама типа из Сибири
literally brought children to us, like
вот к нам привозили детей буквально типа
there  from the first grade to the ninth grade they
там от с первого класса по девятый класс
bring children from Belgorod because they are
приво дете из Белгорода потому что их
bombed very heavily This is where in
бомбят очень сильно Это куда в
Siberia in the Khanty-Mansiysk Autonomous Okrug KhMA game there is cold this is why
Сибирь в ХМАО хма игра там холодина это
they were brought from warm Belgorod to the KhMA game
их из Белгорода тёплого в хма игру
Yes because they are located they are
повезли Да потому что они находятся их
bombed How many years already can it be
бомбят Сколько уже 2 года может ри
brutal  they lived peacefully if it weren't for this
жесть они спокойно жили если бы не это
war, it's
война
true. And these de all at vre
правда И эти де все у вре
if the children left the child in
если дети дите оставили в
Belgorod, like the children were sent
Белгороде типа детей отправили потому
because they said that at least it was necessary to preserve the
что сказали что хотя бы нужно сохранить
young
типа молодое
generation. That is, it turns out that the children, first,
поколение То есть получается дети первый
second, third grade, without parents, are sitting in the
второй третий класс без родители сидят в
Small Game A  where do they live there And in our
Малой игре А где они там живут А у нас в
hotels volunteers teachers look after them
отелях за ними присматривают волонтёры
teachers look after them like this
учителя педагоги за за ними вот тако вот
they look after them very well
зани очень хорошо следят
already without
уже так без
parents for 2 years about a year a year yes Well
родителей 2 года примерно год год да Ну
this is some kind of nonsense No seriously It's
это какой-то бред Нет серьёзно Это
because they bomb like this  it's because of the
потому что вот так вот бомбят это из-за
war maybe about some orphanages
войны может о каких-то там детдомовских
or something or no no no no no no no
или что или нет нет нет нет нет нет нет
Cool This might not be from
Прикольно Это може не из самого
Belgorod itself But these are from  Belgorod
Белгорода А вот этих из Белгородской
region from border areas yes they
области из приграничных районов да
cast border yes yes yes like I
отлили граничных да дадада типа мне
literally I was there with one guy reporting
буквально я там с одним пацаном сообщала
he was showing a video of him standing And like
он показывают видео как он стоит И вот
that like that a drone rocket is flying over him
так вот типа вот над ним летит что Дрон
I didn't understand So what is this specifically
ракета Я не поняла Так что это конкретно
He said that like we are used to  these are already
Он сказал что типа мы привыкли уже это
children from Belgorod yes
именно дети из Белгорода да
yes damn So Well this is scary Here is my
Да капец Так что Ну это страшно Вот мой
ex-boyfriend who supposedly lived
молодой человек бывший который типа жил
in Ukraine
в Украине
and I heard He told me like our
а я слышала Он мне говорил типа у нас
Internet is being turned off like I won't be online
выключает интернет типа я не буду в сети
that here we have announced this uh
то что вот у нас объявили этот э
what  threat air raid siren yes yes
что угрозу воздушная тревога да да
air raid siren I just heard all these
воздушную тревогу я прям слышала все эти
flashing lights here BC and he from which
мигалки вот ВС а он с какой с какого
city do you have
города у тебя
Oh I don't remember anymore And which city was he from do you
Ой я уже не А с какого он был
remember I don't remember anymore well that was your
помнишь я не помню уже ну это у тебя
boyfriend back when it turned out even before
парень ещё когда был получается ещё до
the war  No, he literally in September so And
войны Нет он буквально в сентябре так А
how could he from Ukraine be your boyfriend
как он из Украины мог быть твоим парнем
you met remotely yes Yes I
вы дистанционно встречались да Да
had to e times look it started his he
приходилось е раз смотри началось сво он
lived in Ukraine you are in Russia How did you
жил в Украине ты в России Как вы
meet on the
познакомились через
Internet and never saw each other in person
интернет и вживую не виделись никогда
no And now  I just when they say My
нет А теперь я просто когда говорят Мой
boyfriend I somehow Jordan Justin
парень я как-то Джордана Джастину
Justin understood I just the phrase my I am still
Джастина понял Я просто фразу мой я ещё
old-fashioned Yes I am 43 years old as if in my
старомодный Да мне 43 года как бы в моей
youth the concept my boyfriend and my
молодости понятие мой парень и моя
girlfriend it was well when we somehow
девушка это было ну когда мы как-то
see each other meet and now on the
видимся встречаемся а теперь по
Internet  Cool
интернету Прикольно да
yeah, but how is that possible? You
м а как это так получается ты с ним
met him online, yeah. What's the
встречалась по интернету да А в чём
catch? He couldn't come because
фокус а он не мог же приехать потому что
in order to get to Russia He had to
чтобы заехать в Россию Ему нужно было
go around like from Belarus there, yeah, he
объехать типа с Беларуси там ну да он
can't come. That's why. Cool
никак не заедет Да его потому Прикольно
yeah  And so I also wouldn't be able to come to him
да И вот я бы тоже к нему не смогла
because like If you
приехать потому что типа Если бы вы
found out that I'm from Russia then I understood everything about my
узнали что я из России то всё у меня
rantos
ранты тоже понял
and why did you break up
а почему разошлись
he was just an [ __ ] everything there is like
вы он просто был мудаком всё там типа
just an
просто
[ __ ] cool some kind of 21st
[__] прикольно какието отношения XXI
century interesting relationship
века интересные
Yes I understand A  ok but for example
Да понял А хорошо а вот например у вас
what do your relatives say about the war how do
родственники что говорят про войну как
they look at it
они на это
Well we all understand how the older
смотрят Ну все мы понимаем как старшее
generation reacts to all this
поколение на всё это реагирует
that is
то есть
well negatively
ну негативно
of course
конечно
Who what nothing nothing
Кто что не ничего не
what I say imagine if we have a
что я говорю представляете если мы будем
conversation on tiktok you record me  V  tiktok
разговор Вы записываете меня в tiktok
Dania Kato
Даня Като
blo scared me with tiktok I don't like
бло напугали меня тиктоком я не люблю
publicity that's what we do too yeah And look and it
публичности вот мы тоже да А смотрите а
turns out like uh food prices
получается как бы ээ продукты цены как
have grown because of all
Выросли из-за всего
this well we have a lot of sanctions a
этого ну у нас же санкций очень
lot of sanctions and a lot of products
много санкций и очень много продуктов
have gone but we have them  from Turkey
ушло но у нас у нас ведут из Турции
Kazakhstan Belarus
Казахстана Белоруссии
That is, we have a lot of these
То есть у нас очень много таких вот
Where do they bring and naturally these products
Откуда везут и естественно эти продукты
Well, twice as much, that is, we have
Ну в два раза больше то есть у нас
Coca-Cola, almost 200 rubles a
кока-кола почти 200 руб стоит
liter, but that's a lot Well, yes, eggs 126
литр но это очень много Ну да яйца 126
rubles eggs 126 rubles like milk there  150 rubles
руб яйца 126 руб типа молоко там 150 руб
We have Well, expensive bread, almost
У нас стоят Ну дорого хлеб почти
a hundred, that is, well, expensive Yes, the prices are high And who are you
сотку то есть ну дорого Да цены выс А вы
studying to be, honey, we are doctors Yes, doctors Well,
на кого учитесь меди мы врачи Да врачи
yes, I heard now that you even have
Ну да это сейчас я слышал что у вас даже
some kind of problem with saline solution in
проблема с физраствором какая-то в
Russia No, there is no shortage of saline solution  there
России Нет не нехватка физраствора не
was no no about medical
была нет нетт насчёт медицинских
drugs We are all good we have everything
препаратов У нас всё хорошо у нас всё
sorted out and they started bringing from Kazakhstan they
уладили да привозить стали с Казахстана
bring us a lot of medicines Yes, at
нам привозят очень много медикаментов Да
first Yes, it's true like  I
вот первое время Да правда типа у меня я
have to take pills and they couldn't
вот должна пить таблетки и мне не могли
find them for me. Well, at first it was
их найти Вот это да первое время было
hard. Now it seems like everything is
тяжеловато Да сейчас вроде всё
fine. I understand. Well, do you
нормально понял А хорошо вот э у вас
have any acquaintances? That's how I understand
есть какие-то знакомые вот я так понимаю
Uncle Mobil Zro. That's how he was called. Is there
дядю мобили Зро так его призвали А есть
anyone?  then whoever went to war signed up
кто-то кто сам пошёл на войну записался
for a contract yes yes a lot of them too Well,
на контракт да да очень много тоже Ну у
I have acquaintances like that, like
меня вот из таких знакомых это типа ну
my peers
мои ровесники
like those who left voluntarily yes like not the
типа кто ушёл добровольно да типа не
adult generation left voluntarily But
взрослое поколение ушло добровольно А
those of our
вот именно нашего
age like they go instead of
возраста типа они идут вместо отцов
their fathers Yes in  I mean instead of fathers already
своих Да в смысле вместо отцы уже
died fathers are called they go instead of
погибли отцов призывают они идут вместо
them how is it fathers are called they go
них как это отцов призывают они идут
instead of them I didn't understand anything Well it's just
вместо них ничего не понял Ну просто
like they come and say Hello
типа они приходят говорят Здраствуйте
like they called such and such I am his son
типа вызвали такого такого-то я его сын
I want to go instead of
Я хочу пойти вместо
him PP
него ПП
when s is on Bat I will go  instead of you and
при с горит Бат я пойду вместо тебя и
bat let's
бат давай
short scandals there VS they just
короче скандалами там ВС они просто
secretly leave they just secretly leave and
тайно уходят они просто тайно уходят и
stat their fact they take me not some how
стат их фак меня забирают не какойто как
can secretly like found out that batya is
может тайно типа узнал что батя заме
replacing already
нето уже
generally want
вообще хотите
all centuries was that as if parents  something
все века было что как бы родители что-то
for the sake of children something is sacrificed Yes because
ради детей чем-то жертвуют Да потому что
they are the future of the generation you are already yours
как бы они будущее поколения ты уже своё
as if
как бы
squeezing to save the younger
отжим чтобы сохранить более молодое
generation because it will continue to
поколение потому что оно дальше будет
live it will reproduce the
жить оно будет воспроизводить
family in the same way it seems to me differently they are
род в же по-разному мне кажется они
about here I heard  that in Ukraine
про вот я слышала что в Украине сильно
they take away a lot of guys well we have mobilization
забирают парней ну у нас мобилизация
just like you have
есть так же как у вас мобилизация есть
mobilization But we don't have such a mobilization no Well
Так у нас не такая мобилизация не Ну у
you just took everyone away at once
вас у вас просто за один раз всех
Yes so for 300,000 people
забрали Да так за вот 300.000 людей у
here it's temporary of course yes  we have
нас она временно идёт конечно да у нас
been declared mobilization and
объявлена мобилизация и
those liable for military service are being looked at in certain
военнообязанных смотрят по определённым
areas according to certain criteria Yes, they are
областям по определённым критериям Да
taking it, it's
берут
war, we didn't have mobilization, there
война у нас не было мобилизации есть
was mobilization, so they only called up
была мобилизация так он призвали лишь
the uncle who got hit in
дядю которому Дрон прилетел в
the head by a drone Well, then they would have taken mine Well, they didn't
голову Ну тогда бы моих забрали Ну не
take everyone, they won't take everyone Well, okay,
всех забрали всех же не заберут Ну ладно
that's okay  a huge number of where
это ж огромное количество где их
to put them where to train them where to give them weapons
посадить где их обучить где их оружие им
so Vitaly it's clear Understandable And another
дать так Витали же понятно Понятно А ещё
question turns out like this What do you
такой вопрос получается вот Как вы
think I well I don't live in Russia
считаете я ну я не живу в России
but I studied economic geography  at
но я изучал экономическую географию в
school and we are told that Russia
школе и нам рассказывают что Россия
has huge reserves of gold gas
имеет огромные запасы золота газа
diamonds oil and sells it to the whole world.
алмазов нефти продаёт это всему миру вот
I can't understand why little
я не могу понять почему маленькая
Estonia without oil gas diamonds lives
Эстония без нефти газ алмазов живёт
richer than Russia with oil gas and
богаче чем Россия с нефтью газами и
diamonds. And how can we understand that it lives richer, like the
алмазами А как понять богаче живёт как
salary level is higher, like the level  life is
уровень зарплат выше типа уровень жизни
higher in Estonia damn the minimum wage is
выше в Эстонии блин минимальная зарплата
three times more than in Russia
в три раза больше чем в России
because they don't have it doesn't go War so
потому что у них нет не идёт Война так
before the war even before the war So
до войны даже до войны Так вы почему а
why do you think that we lived like well
почему вы думаете что мы жили типа ну
Russia was well I see the minimum
Россия была ну я смотрю минимальную
wage in Estonia is  Russia in Estonia
зарплату в Эстонии в России в Эстонии
above average
выше средни
you Yes look in Russia now in Estonia now now
вы Да смотри в России сейчас в Эстонии
now I will say for sure
сейчас сейчас сейчас скажу точно
shiba so minimum so so so in
шиба так минимальный так так так в
Estonia
Эстонии
2024 Let's take the data for the fourth year
2024 Давайте за д четвёртый год возьму
so 820 euros This is the minimum
данные так 820 евро Это минимальная
wage by your standards yes it turns out
зарплата по вашим меркам да получается
85,000 rubles minimum wage in
85.000 руб минимальная зарплата в
Estonia A in Russia 16 I think the
Эстонии А в России 16 по-моему
minimum wage is
МРОТ
2024 Vo and in Russia 19,000 rubles That is,
2024 Во а в России 19.000 руб То есть
it turns out to be the minimum wage  Russia
получается минимальная зарплата России
more than four times exceeds oh in
больше чем в четыре раза превышает ой в
Estonia twice more than in
Эстонии вче раза больше че чем в
Russia math still we understand that
России математи все же мы понимаем что
no well we don't get 16,000 so clearly yes
не ну мы не получаем 16.000 так ясно да
And there it doesn't work out then I see
И там не получается то я смотрю
the minimum is less That is if we
минимальная меньше То есть если мы
take the average in Russia yes  Or the
возьмём средняя в России да Или
median will be less than the
медианная она будет меньше чем
minimum in Estonia, you know. Well,
минимальная в Эстонии понимаете Ну
now we have raised salaries for
сейчас у нас очень подняли зарплаты и
doctors and teachers a lot. Well, how much does a
врачам и педагогам Ну сколько в
teacher get in Smolensk? Let's
Смоленске педагог получает Давай сейчас
look now. Now, Smolensk,
смотрим сейчас Смоленск
teacher's salary. So,
учителя так вот
look at the data from city rabot.ru, the average
смотри по данным город работ ру средняя
teacher's salary in Smolensk 2, whose year?
зарплата учителя в Смоленске 2 чей год
26,000 rubles, that is, in Estonia the minimum
26.000 руб то есть в Эстонии минимальная
salary is 85,000 rubles, and in Smolensk
зарплата 85.000 руб а в Смоленске
the average average for a teacher is
средняя средняя для учителя
24 teachers receive
24 учителя получают
26,000 when they went only after
26.000 когда они пошли только после
university, it goes like an internship, the average
университета идёт как стажировка средняя
salary of a teacher in Russia, oh, in
зарплата педагога в России ой в
Smolensk specifically because like we
Смоленске конкретно потому что типа мы
asked my friend herself is studying at
спрашивали у меня сама подруга учится на
They have a teacher for 70,000  80,000
педагога у них ну 70.000 80.000 потому
because they constantly have bonuses I don't
что у них постоянно идут премиальные не
know Well look I'm taking
знаю Ну смотри я вот беру статистика
salary statistics official data there is no such
зарплат официальные данные нету таких
80,000 average that is maybe even let's go
80.000 средни то есть может даже давай
even if 80 is average it means that
если даже 80 средняя то это значит что
someone gets more someone less yes
кто-то получает больше кто-то меньше да
And in Estonia it's mini  in Estonia the minimum is
А в Эстонии мини в Эстонии минимальная
85 you know about now the median salary of a
85 понимаешь о сейчас медианная зарплата
teacher in Smolensk
учителя в Смоленске
now but
сейчас а вот в
what about this question
чём при данного вопро
asked why Russia has oil gas
спросил почему У России есть нефть газ
diamonds Yes gold but they live poorer than in
алмазы Да золото а живут беднее чем в
Estonia Well lucky territorially Well the
Эстонии Ну повезло территориально Так ну
geographical location
географическое расположение так
allows it Well Estonia Well just not
позволяет Ну Эстония Ну просто не
won the geographical position
выиграла географическое положение такое
like Russia and in principle the country even
как у России и в принципе страны даже
just Well, compare the scale of the countries That
просто Ну вот Сравни масштабы стран То
is, as if it is already clear that Russia has an
есть как бы уже понятно что у России как
advantage and in geographical
бы преимущество и в географическом
position forget that Russia is a
положении забывайте что Россия являе
big country with us with people correctly
большой страной у нас с людей правильно
look again at Russia  geographical
ещё раз смотрите у России географическое
advantage oil gas diamonds more
преимущество нефть газ алмазы больше
territory more people why does it live
территории больше людей почему живёт
poorer than small Estonia with
беднее маленькой Эстонии с
bad because Russia is a big country
плохим потому что Россия большая страна
and Estonia is small and it is easier for Estonia
а Эстония маленькая и эстони легче
to raise the economy than for Russia  I understood that
поднять экономику чем России понял то
is, I get it, I understand correctly that
есть получа я я правильно понимаю что
in order to be a rich country you need to
для того чтобы быть богатой страной надо
become a small
стать маленькой
country so so Well, you said you
страной так так Ну вы же сказали вы
said that Estonia is richer because
сказали что Эстония богаче потому что
it is small it is easier for it, and Russia is big it is more
она маленькая ей проще а Россия большая
difficult for it, then maybe it would be better for Russia to
ей сложнее то может России тогда лучше
split into 30 small ones
разбиться на 30 маленьких государств
there are no states to make it easier and then why should
чтобы было легче нет а ВЧ зачем тогда
Russia be
России быть
big because
большой потому что
Russia because it is Russia Russia
Россия потому что это Россия Россия
should always be big because
должна быть всегда большой потому что у
we have big souls and strong
нас большие души и сильные
people I didn't understand anything just Look I I'm
люди ничего не понял просто Смотри Я я
not I can't understand the logic Yes, Estonia
не я не могу понять Логику Да в Эстонии
is good  because it is small it is easier for it
хорошо потому что она маленькая ей проще
Why then should Russia be big Why should
А зачем тогда России быть большой Зачем
regions unite into the Russian
регионам объединяться в Российскую
Federation Yes, let each region be
Федерацию Да пусть вот каждый регион был
with a separate country small and be
бы с отдельной страной маленькой и
governed better and live
управлялся лучше и жил
richer And why are you asking this to an
богаче А что почему Вы спрашиваете это у
eighteen-year-old Idina de vo We are studying
восемнадцатилетний идина де во Мы учимся
at a
в
medical school  anatomy about what illnesses you
медвуз анатомию про какие у вас болячки
may have but not about
могут быть но не про
economics more sdi we
экономику более сди
don't understand some aspects I will explain
не понимаем некоторых аспектов я объясню
I am not interested in communicating with some
мне не интересно общаться с какими-то
deputies because I am a simple person
депутатами потому что я простой человек
from Ukraine and I am interested in simple
из Украины и мне интересно с простыми
people Yes in some things I know better  in something
людьми Да в чём-то я лучше знаю в чём-то
you, we are like ordinary people Yes, we are not
вы вот мы как простые люди Да мы не
deputies, not politicians Yes, but we also want to
депутаты не политики Да но мы хотим тоже
understand somehow We live in this world
как-то понимать Это мы живём в этом мире
Yes, we communicate And why is it so And why is it so
Да мы общаемся А почему так А почему так
We have some kind of our own idea
у нас есть какое-то своё представление
Yes, gods But we are people Yes  and we still kind of
да боги Но мы люди Да и мы всё-таки как
build our states we elect
бы строим свои государства мы избираем
presidents deputies you elect what do you
президентов депутатов вы избира что вы
want from us except that's what you
хотите вот от нас кроме вот что вы
ask us What tricky
спрашиваете у нас Какие каверзные
questions are these not caverns you just want
вопросы это не каверны просто вы хотите
wait can I say you want to
подождите можно до говорю вы хотите
identify the pros and cons of Russia
выявить плюсы типа и минусы России
right no no no I want to understand Where
правильно нене не я хочу понять Куда
does all the money go from gold gas oil
деваются все деньги от золота газа нефти
and diamonds coca we
и алмазов коку знаем
all understand And what do you
всем этим понима А как вы
think we don't think about such things We are studying at a
думаете мы не думаем о таком Мы учимся в
medical school we don't have time to think about such things
медвуз у нас нет времени о таком думать
honestly okay Then then a more cunning
честно хорошо Тогда тогда хитрее
question for you As for children  which Well there are
вопрос вам Как детям которые Ну там
young people who study at a medical
молодёжи которые учатся в медицинском
university the question is why a doctor in Estonia
ВУЗе вопрос почему медик в Эстонии
Why a doctor in the USA Why a doctor in Canada
Почему медик в США Почему медик в Канаде
gets more than a doctor in Russia this is a
получает больше чем медик в России это
real question for you doctors
вопрос уже вот реальный для вас медиков
Wait do you know how much a doctor
Подождите а вы знаете сколько
earns and a doctor in the USA and in Russia
зарабатывает а медик в США и в России
does not  really real numbers have you seen
нет прямо реально цифры вы видели
the salary of doctors now doctors in the USA I'll
зарплату у медиков сейчас медик США я
tell you How much is a doctor in Russia
тебе скажу Ты сколько медик в России
First tell me Well let's take
Сначала скажи Ну вы давайте возьмём вот
surgeons Yes, the most difficult profession in the
хирургов Да самую сложную профессию в
medical field They get Well, quite a
медицинской сфере Они же получают Ну
lot of money How much
достаточно огромные деньги Сколько скоко
Let's take Moscow Moscow how much And
Давайте возьмём Москву Москву сколько А
surgeons  they charge for one operation how
хирурги берут за одну операцию сколько
much how much does a surgeon get in
сколько сколько хирург получает в
Russia minimum 500 Yes it seems to me
России минимально 500 Да мне кажется
because the prices for operations are huge
потому что цены на операции они огромные
and people do them wait again let's do
и люди их делают подожди ещё раз давай
it surgeon in Russia how much
так хирург в России сколько
does a surgeon get in Russia here is a specific
получает хирург в России вот конкретно
territorial city Tell us we will
территориально город Скажите мы вам
tell you here is yours
скажем вот ваш
Smolensk 400 minimum 4,000 dollars
Смоленск 400 минимальная 4.000 долларов
Yes, it's a month Now let's see
Да это месяц Сейчас посмотрим
so well we're talking about doctors who don't
так ну мы говорим про врачей которые не
work for the state wait wait
работают на государство подожди подожди
wait wait now now So so I
подожди подожди сейчас сейчас Так так я
see the salary of a surgeon in
смотрю зарплата хи зарплата хирурга в
Smolensk for the twenty-fourth year the
Смоленске за двадцать четвёртый год
average salary is 82,000 rubles no Where are
средняя зарплата 82000 руб не А откуда
they from  I take the numbers
они такие цифры беру
lo This is not true at all Well, what is written
ло Это вообще не так Ну то что написано
somewhere, but it says yes, the average salary of a
где-то а вот пишет да средняя зарплата
surgeon in  Smolensk reached 90,000 rubles
хирурга в Смоленске достигла 90.000 руб
where did you get it? Show me at least one
откуда у вас Покажите мне хоть одну
vacancy on the Internet where it says that
вакансию вот в интернете где пишет что
the salary of a surgeon will be 200,000,
зарплата будет э хирурга 200.000
for example, or 300 or
например или там 300 или
400. Well, this is what the
400 Ну это же написано то сколько
state pays. No, these are private surgeon vacancies.
государство Нет это вакансии хирурга
Also, vacancies are published by
частные также э вакансии публикуются от
private clinics
частных клиник
for the sake of  interest Yes, you as doctors
ради интереса Да вот вы как медики
yes work in Akhta in Moscow nurse from
да работа в Ахта в Москве медсестра от
105,000 in Moscow Everything in Moscow yes in
105.000 в Москве Всё в Москве да в
Moscow here in your Let's in Smolensk
Москве вот в вашем Давайте в Смоленске
Take that is nurse
Возьмите то есть медсестра
Mak
Мак
this is Leninsky district Smolensk city
это Ленинский район Смоленский город
Smolensk city
Смоленск город
oh ho Okay let's do it all nurse believed
ой хо Ладно давай всё медсестра поверила
1000  dollars a nurse has per month
1000 долларов медсестра в месяц имеет
So how much does a doctor have this is from a doctor
Так сколько имеет врач это от врач
How much does a doctor
Сколько Врач
have
имеет
so here is a dentist-surgeon
так вот стоматолог-хирург
dentist-surgeon
стоматолог-хирург
how much from 70 maximum upper ceiling of a
сколько от 70 максимум верхний потолок
surgeon 3000 dollars
хирурга 3000 долларов
so So this is where we have Cherepovets in general
так Так это у нас где Череповец вообще
because Smolensk does not give me if
потому что Смоленск мне не выдаёт если
anything Okay now  look I'm looking at your
че Хорошо теперь смотри я тебе смотрю
salary  doctors Yes doctors salary in the USA
зарплата врачей Да зарплата врачей в США
in 2004 24 yes On your resource dn
в 2004 24 году да На вашем ресурсе дн
average annual earnings of doctors in
средний годовой заработок врачей в 2004
2004 reached 350,000 dollars divided by
году достигне 350.000 долларов делим на
12 it turns out 29,000 dollars per month
12 это получается 29000 долларов в месяц
that is for your money for your money it
то есть на ваши деньги на ваши деньги
turns out
получается
that 30,000 dollars it turns out 3 million  a
что 30.000 долларов это получается 3 млн
doctor in the US gets 3 million rubles a month
врач в США получает 3 млн рублей в месяц
but don't forget that the prices there are also
но вы не забываете что там цены тоже
much higher no no no you'll
намного выше ещё не не не ты сейчас
look now yes look that is the doctor No matter
посмотришь да смотри то есть у врача
what figures you show an
Какие б ты не показывала цифры
American doctor gets 10 times
американский врач получает раз в 10
more at least 10 times more  here we are
больше как минимум в 10 раз вот мы
just prices for food
только цены на продукты
No No No No look at prices for bananas the
Нет Нет Нет Нет посмотри цены на бананы
same prices they won't be 10 times
такие же цены на они не будут в 10 раз
more iPhone doesn't cost 10 times more in
больше iPhone не стоит в 10 раз дороже в
America true car doesn't cost 10
Америке правда автомобиль не стоит в 10
times more look at technology in America is
раз дороже смотри техника в Америке
cheaper than in Russia  yes the mortgage is cheaper the
дешевле чем в России да ипотека дешевле
mortgage there is 2% And you have 21% debt 08 What is the
ипотека там 2% А у вас 21% дол 08 Какой
current
сейчас
dollar exchange rate Zero  add 100
долла Нолика допис 100
consider Well 160 rubles approximately And here
считай Ну 160 руб примерно что А у нас
bananas cost 70 rubles twice Look,
бананы стоят 70 руб в два Вот смотри
your bananas are twice as cheap Look again,
ваши бананы в два раза ещё раз смотри
your bananas are twice as cheap And
ваши бананы в два раза дешевле А
salaries in America are 10 times higher
зарплаты в Америке в 10 раз больше то
That is, an American can buy with his salary,
есть американец на свою зарплату может
you understand  what are you trying to do now?
купить понимаете что вы сейчас пытаетесь
And to prove to us that in America they get
А нам доказать то что в Америке получает
higher salaries despite the fact that their prices are
зарплаты больше при том что у них цены
279, you got it here. Look, look, look,
вы тут 279 допер Да смотри смотри смотри
look again, you just
смотри ещ раз ты только что по бананам
said something about bananas. You said some random
ты по бананам сказала какие-то Рандомные
bananas. We got it.  In America,
бананы взяли мы поняли что в Америке
bananas are only twice as expensive, but the
бананы всего в два раза дороже но
salary is 10 times higher. That is, as a
зарплата выше в 10 раз То есть как
mathematician, I will say that an
математик скажу что на свою зарплату
American can buy five times
американец Может в пять раз купить
more bananas with his salary than a Russian. That is, he can buy five times more bananas than a Russian. For
больше бананов чем россиянин То есть он
some reason, the unemployment rate in the US is the same,
пять при этом почему-то в США уровень
and so
безработиц и в таком
let's  let's not forget
Давайте не будем ещё Забывать про том
that in Russia free medicine is like
что в России бесплатная медицина типа
much cheaper insurance We have a
намного дешевле страховка У нас очень
lot of free things that in the US you have to
много всего бесплатного что в США нужно
pay
платить
money A  now tell me you as a
бабки А теперь расскажи мне вот ты как
future medic Yes tell me about
медик будущий Да расскажи мне про
free medicine in the Russian
бесплатную медицину в Российской
Federation good Medina but
Федерации хорошая Медина но
why do you have some private
Зачем У вас есть какие-то частные
clinics with such huge salaries
клиники с такими огромными зарплатами
As you
Как ты
say because in a private
говоришь потому что в частной
clinic people come there you
поликлиники туда приходят люди у кото
know And we have  a lot of people are
понимаете А у нас очень много людей
right paid medicine is a basic
правильно платная медицина - это базовый
range of services that can help a
спектр услуг которые могут помочь
person and paid clinics are
человеку а платные клиники - это уже
more in-depth, they found cancer in me I
более углублённо вот у меня рак нашли Я
won't go and take these
же бесплатно не пойду сдавать эти
tests for free and cancer in Russia is not a
анализы и к бесплатно рак в России не
flight for free I heard correctly well it is a flight but  you
полет я правильно услышал ну полет но ты
will still collect money
всё равно будешь собирать деньги на то
to make you more global
чтобы сделать тебе более глобальную
help because well, what is
помощь потому что ну так в чём
free of charge? Don't hang out please I want to
бесплатность не Зависай пожалуйста хочу
talk So it was just a quintessence
говорить Так это как раз была квинтесса
with these
вот с этими с
doctors free
врачами бесплатная
medicine And why then all these
медицина А зачем тогда все эти клиники
paid clinics that have fabulous sums there
платные которые там баснословные суммы
surgeons get it in private
хирурги получают тогда в платных
clinics because they'll give you Well, I'll
клиниках потому что тебе там дадут Ну
put some green stuff on your
зелёнкой помажу
forehead, they'll prescribe mustard plasters and
лоб горчичники пропишут и глюконо
calcium gluconate, they'll tell you I'll prescribe it,
кальция скаже Выпишу ска
go ahead And if you have  cancer Go somewhere
иди А если у тебя рак Иди куда-то
there it was about bombs it was about
туда это было про бомби это про было
they broke off Oh right it's just
они сорвались Ах прям это Просто
quintessence Yeah right cancer Yes you get it for free
квинтесс Да ну рак Да тебе бесплатно сде
but you still have to collect
но тебе всё равно придётся собирать
money Yes if you have cancer you get it for free
деньги Да если у тебя рак тебе бесплатно
then you still have to
будет то тебе всё равно придётся
collect money but  in America medicine is
собирать деньги но в Америке медицина
bad I love it it was a bombastic
плохая я люблю это было бомбический
dressing down like subscribe comment and send
разнос лайк подписка коммент и скиньте
this video to all your friends doctors Glory to
всем знакомым медикам этот видос Слава
Ukraine write to my Telegram right now
Украине пись на мий Telegram прямо зараз
axis VN
ось ВН
apok this is very and very important YouTube takes
апок це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube заня
us through scarg ORV in your ban and very
нас через скарг ОРВ в твый бан и дуже
many videos not  I show people sometimes I don't
багато вдео не показую людям вчасно не
show information about streams. That's why I
показуе информация про стрими Тому для
write the latest news right now, and while there's a
пишиться прямо зараз а пок там в
telegram where we'll find
телеграме окрим видео ще теж
interesting and useful information, we'll be glad to help
цикава и корисна информация и мы повинни
you with the latest news and news
з вами тримати постийний оперативный
regardless of whether we'll show you that.  about this
незалежно в того чи покаже вам про це
YouTube Glory to Ukraine
YouTube Слава украини
subscribe L
подпишись L